原视频名：Hubble's Latest Problems May Be In a 50 Year Old Computer Design
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/RWUnC2uf3XY
原视频发布日期：20210630
字幕翻译：旋火
hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
For the last two weeks
在过去的两个星期里
scientists at NASA have been trying to bring the Hubble Space Telescope back online
NASA的科学家们一直在努力使哈勃太空望远镜重新上线
after it suffered a computer failure.
在它遭遇计算机故障之后
Now this isn't the main computer.
那么这不是主计算机
this is a small payload computer that coordinates the operation of the various scientific instruments.
这是一个小型有效载荷计算机 用于协调各种科学仪器的运行
It's called the scientific instrument control and data handling unit
它被称为科学仪器控制和数据处理单元
and within that there is a computer called the NASA Standard Spaceflight Computer.
而在这里面有一台计算机被称为NASA标准航天计算机
So on Sunday June 13th at around 4pm they experienced some sort of problem
所以在6月13日星期日下午4点左右 他们遇到了某种问题
that caused the computer to halt down into a safe mode
导致计算机停止运行 进入了安全模式
and they've been trying to bring it back online ever since.
而从那时起 他们一直在努力使其重新上线
Initially it looked like they were having trouble reading and writing from memory units
起初 他们似乎在内存单元的读写上遇到了问题
and the good news was that this computer has four memory units available to it.
而好消息是 这台计算机有四个内存单元可用
Four banks of 64k of memory and it could switch between any of those
计算机可在四组64K的内存中的任何一组之间切换
and they decided to switch over to a backup memory unit
而他们决定切换到一个备份内存单元
and unfortunately have seen the same problem.
不幸的是 遇到了同样的问题
So then the thought was perhaps it's a problem with the computer itself
因此 他们认为这可能是计算机本身的问题
and the good news is this is again designed with redundancy.
好消息是 这又是冗余设计的
There's an entire backup computer core that they could switch to.
他们可以切换到一个完整的备份计算机核心
So an identical NASA spaceflight computer.
也就是一个完全相同的NASA航天计算机
So they switched over to that.
那么他们切换到了那台上面
They switched to an appropriate memory bank
同时也切换到一个适当的内存组
and they ran their tests
并进行了测试
and again they're finding that as they would write to memory
而他们再次发现 写入内存的时候
they wouldn't necessarily be able to read the results back.
不一定能够读回结果
So that's the easy fixes.
那么 这是容易解决的问题
They are still looking at other possibilities.
他们仍在研究其他的可能性
Like the memory can be written to directly by other units.
比如内存可以被其他单元直接写入
The computer actually sits on an entire board called the science instrument control and data handling unit
计算机实际上位于一个叫做科学仪器控制和数据处理单元的整个电路板上
and on there there are control units and science data formatters
在那里有控制单元和科学数据格式化单元
which talk directly to the instruments and can write data into the memory.
直接与仪器对话 并可以将数据写入内存
And that might be causing a problem.
而这可能会造成一个问题
There's also a conjecture that there may be a problem with the power supply
也有一种猜测 可能是电源出现了问题
which may be generating the incorrect voltage
它可能产生了不正确的电压
and therefore the rights aren't going through correctly.
因此 数据不能正常写入
I mean we've all been worried about the gyros and the reaction wheels on this the Hubble
我的意思是 我们都在担心这个哈勃上的陀螺仪和反作用轮
when it turns out that the computer might be the thing that ultimately kills it.
而事实证明 计算机可能是最终杀死它的东西
But I hope they fix this problem.
但我希望他们能解决这个问题
but while you're here I kind of do want to talk about the computers on the Hubble Space Telescope.
但既然你来了 我确实想再谈谈哈勃太空望远镜上的计算机
This particular computer the NASA Standard Spaceflight Computer has its roots going back almost 50 years.
这台特殊的计算机 即NASA标准航天计算机 其可追溯到近50年前
The first instance of a computer with this design flying was in 1972 on the Orbiting Astronomical Observatory C.
这种设计的计算机的第一次飞行是在1972年的轨道天文观测台C上
Back then it was called the on-board processor
那时 它被称为板载处理器
and so this telescope was a space telescope.
那么这个望远镜是一个太空望远镜
But it was designed to look in the X-ray and the extreme ultraviolet.
但它被设计用来观察X射线和极紫外光
Now back then integrated circuits weren't particularly high density.
那么 那时的集成电路还不是特别高密度
It took 1700 chips to make this thing work.
它需要1700个芯片来正常工作
Each having a handful of gates on each chip
每个芯片上都有少量的门电路
so those would be on little like six by six inch boards
那么 芯片被放在差不多15.24厘米乘15.24厘米的小板上
and you would have a stack of about 125 of these that would make up your computer
而一个堆栈有大约125个这样的处理器 来组成计算机
so it would weigh quite a bit.
那么它的重量是相当大的
The first flight used core memory and it had four banks of 4096 words.
第一次飞行使用了磁芯存储器(一种内存) 它有四组4096个字
But these were 18 bit words.
但这些是18位的字
They chose 18 bits because they wanted to have 4k of memory access.
他们选择18位是因为他们希望有4k的内存访问
They needed 12 address bits.
他们需要12个地址位
But they wanted the instructions to be encoded and they needed an index bit
但他们希望对指令进行编码 所以需要一个索引位
so they had five bits for the instructions that gave them 32 different instructions.
指令有5位 这样就有32个不同的指令
And an index bit which tells them
还有一个索引位 告诉他们
that the address that follows may be relative to some address that's in the register.
后面的地址可能是相对于寄存器中的某个地址的偏移
And anyway as a result all the arithmetic operations would operate on 18 bit fixed point numbers
总之 所有的算术运算都是在18位的定点数上进行的
and that was apparently enough for them to be able to perform all the scientific operations that they needed.
而这显然足以进行所有所需的科学运算
So anyway the Orbiting Astronomical Observatory C kept working for 10 years.
那么无论如何 轨道天文台C保持了10年的运行
It did great service to a science.
为一门学科做出了巨大的贡献
But in the meantime there were moves to improve the computer
但与此同时 也有改进计算机的举措
so you had the advanced on-board processor.
那么就有了先进板载处理器
And the main thing about this was that they started using medium level of integration.
而其中最主要的是 他们开始使用中等水平的集成电路
So they managed to take the 1700 chips and reduce it down to 69 chips.
所以他们设法把1700个芯片减少到69个芯片
When they built the apollo guidance computer in the 1960s
当他们在60年代建造阿波罗导航计算机时
the integrated circuits they were working with had four gates per chip.
所使用的集成电路 每块芯片有四个逻辑门
For the advanced on-board processor they had bumped that number up to 130 logic gates on every chip.
对于先进板载处理器 他们把这个数字提高到每个芯片上的130个逻辑门
So that computer flew in a couple of the Landsat missions and the International Ultraviolet Explorer.
那么 那台计算机在几个陆地卫星任务和国际紫外线探测卫星中搭载
These had like 4k of memory in the computer.
这些计算机有大约4k的内存
There was not a lot of space to work with.
没有多少空间可以使用
Everything is hand coded in assembly language.
一切都是用汇编语言人工编程的
Finally in 1974 it formally became the NASA Standard Spaceflight Computer
最后在1974年 它正式成为NASA标准航天计算机(NSSC)
and IBM was given the contract
而IBM被授予了合同
because they needed to have a supplier who would be able to consistently deliver this for a long period of time
因为NASA需要一个能长期持续提供这种产品的供应商
The first mission to actually fly with it was the Solar Maximum Mission
第一个真正使用它的航天器是太阳极大期任务卫星
and that launched in 1980.
该航天器于1980年发射
It was also on Landsat D which it launched in 1982
它也出现在1982年发射的陆地卫星D上
and of course the the Hubble Space Telescope or rather the space telescope
当然还有哈勃太空望远镜 或者说太空望远镜
was expected to launch in the middle of the 1980s
原本预计在20世纪80年代中期发射
but because of the Challenger disaster, its launch was delayed until 1990.
但由于挑战者号灾难 其发射被推迟到1990年
So yes a computer architecture designed in the late 1960s
因此 是的 一个在60年代末设计的计算机架构
ended up flying on a spacecraft launched in 1990 with a 64k of core memory.
最终飞上了1990年发射的航天器 其磁芯存储(内存)容量为64K
And these were all integrated onto a single tray with some other important hardware.
而这些都是与其他一些重要的硬件集成在一个支架里的
First of all you had the power unit which would make sure everything got the 28 volts it needed.
首先 得有一个电源单元 其将确保所有硬件所需的28伏电压
And then there were a pair of control unit/science data formatter units
然后有一对控制单元/科学数据格式化单元
and these are important chunks of logic as well
而这些也是重要的逻辑块
because these are the things that talk to the memory.
因为这些是与内存通信的东西
They also talk to the rest of the computers.
同样也与计算机的其他部分进行通信
And they do translation of data between different systems.
会在不同系统之间进行数据转换
For example sending commands to and from the support system modules used 16-bit data
例如 与支持系统模块接受与发送16位的命令
whereas ground system commands would come up with 27 bits
而地面系统的命令会有27位
which is quite unnerving for someone that's been raised in powers of two.
这样的位宽会让一个在2的权威中长大的人变得相当不知所措
So this whole unit was bolted to one of the doors on the space telescope
因此 这整个装置被栓在太空望远镜的一个门上
and it operated fine from the telescope's launch right up until 2008
从望远镜的发射到2008年 它一直运行良好
and when it encountered an unrecoverable failure in one of the redundant systems.
直到它在其中一个冗余系统中遇到了一个无法恢复的故障
And that's fine they continued to operate on the other one
但没关系啊 他们继续在另一个系统上运行
but that was also just as they were preparing for the final servicing mission
但那恰好发生在最后的维护任务做准备的时候
and actually caused them to delay the servicing mission
而且实际上导致他们推迟了维护任务
进行完整更换的是the Science Instrument Command and Data Handling (SIC&DH) Unit，
科学仪器指令和数据处理单元
so that they could get an entire replacement unit on this.
这样他们就可以对这个单元进行完整的替换
But they actually made a few changes to it.
但是他们实际上对它做了一些改变
One of the significant things they did
他们所做的重要事情之一
was they replaced the 64k of core memory with four redundant banks of CMOS memory.
是他们用四组冗余的CMOS存储器替换了64K的核心存储器
So this replacement unit was tested
因此 这个替换单元经过测试
and it was installed during the first EVA on STS-125 on may 14th 2009.
并且在2009年5月14日STS-125的第一次舱外活动(EVA)中被安装
And by the way it was Drew Feustel who actually did this.
顺便说一下 实际上这次任务是由德鲁·福斯泰完成的
This was his first space flight and his first EVA.
这是他的第一次航天飞行以及第一次EVA
He flew to the space station back in 2018 so he's still an active astronaut.
他在2018年曾飞往空间站 所以他仍然是一名现役宇航员
Anyway the other main computer on the Hubble Space Telescope is part of the data management system.
总之哈勃太空望远镜上的另一台主计算机是数据管理系统的一部分
And at its core was originally launched with a DF-224
而在最初发射的时候 其核心是DF-224
which was a space hardened CPU that was slightly more advanced I think than the NSSC.
这是一个辐射硬化CPU 我认为比NSSC稍微先进一些
It was developed in the 1980s by Rockwell and with a clock speed of 1.25 megahertz.
它是在20世纪80年代由洛克威尔开发的 时钟速度为1.25兆赫兹
It wasn't impressing anyone when it was launched in 1990.
其在1990年发射时并没有给任何人留下深刻印象
But of course it was space hardware.
但当然 它是太空设备
It had lots of redundancy.
有很多的冗余
But by 1993 a couple of the redundant memory banks had failed.
但是到了1993年 几个冗余的内存都已失效
And so part of the first servicing mission was to add in a new coprocessor.
因此 第一次维护任务的一部分是添加一个新的协处理器
Apparently it sat on the memory bus and would talk directly to the main CPU
显然 它位于内存总线上 将直接与主CPU通信
but also provide memory redundancy.
但也提供内存冗余
So basically they added a 386 processor with a 387 co-processor to it.
所以基本上他们添加了一个386处理器和一个387协处理器
And the telescope operated with this weird hybrid system for six years
望远镜使用这个奇怪的混合系统运行了6年
until 1999 when Servicing Mission 3A replaced the entire computer with a rather more mundane 486 computer
直到1999年 在维护任务3A中 使用一台更平凡的486计算机取代了整个计算机
which was about 20 times faster than the original DF-224 that it was launched with.
它比最初发射的DF-224快了20倍
That mission incidentally also updated the large data storage
那次任务还顺便更新了大型数据外存
although I've talked about the memory on these things being kilobytes of memory.
尽管我已经说过这些东西的内存有几KB
They have storage for the actual astronomical data.
(同时) 也有实际存储天文数据的外存
Originally it launched with three reel-to-reel tape decks for storage.
最初 在发射时有三个卷轴式磁带台用于外存
But over multiple service missions they started to replace those with solid-state drives
但在多次的维护任务中 他们开始用固态硬盘换掉这些磁带
and on Mission 3A they gave it a 12 gigabyte storage system.
而在3A任务中 他们给它配备了一个12GB的外存系统
It's also worth pointing out that while Hubble has two main computers,
还值得指出的是 虽然哈勃有两台主计算机
it also has a bunch of scientific instruments.
它也有一堆科学仪器
Many of which have been replaced over the lifetime of the telescope.
在望远镜的生命周期中 其中许多已经被替换
So these will have their own computer power
因此 这些仪器将有自己的计算能力
and since some of them are much younger than well the 1970s based computer that runs the the payload
而且由于其中一些计算机比运行有效载荷的1970年代的计算机要年轻得多
it's quite likely that there are more powerful processors in some of the instruments than the NSSC
很可能 在一些仪器上有比NSSC更强大的处理器
which is currently causing us problems.
而此时 NSSC正在导致问题
Finally I'm sure some of you are wondering is it possible to send up a mission to replace this or fix it.
最后 我相信有人想知道 是否有可能派出一个任务来替换它或修复它
Servicing the Hubble Space Telescope was something that really used the capabilities of the Space Shuttle.
为哈勃太空望远镜进行维护是真正利用航天飞机的能力的事情
And there's nothing flying right now that has all those capabilities.
而现在没有任何现役航天器具备所有这些能力
Dragon could certainly rendezvous with it
龙飞船当然可以与它交会
but it doesn't have a manipulator system and doesn't have any ability to perform an EVA.
但它没有机械臂系统 也不能执行EVA
Same with Starliner.
星际客机也是如此
比如带有欧洲机械臂的科学号实验舱？只是拜科努尔打不到哈勃所在低倾角轨道(28.47°)
Nothing Russia has that can do this.
俄罗斯没有任何东西可以做到这一点
Starship. Sure that's going to be big
星船 当然这将是很大的
but it's not currently had any scoping for robotic manipulator systems or EVAs or anything like that.
但它目前没有任何无人机械臂或EVA或类似的东西
So that's very likely a decade of development away if that system proves to work.
因此 等到星船的类似系统得到验证的时候 可能需要10年的开发
We have recently seen the refurbishment of a couple of geostationary satellites using Mission Extension Vehicles
我们最近看到了使用延长任务载具对几颗地球静止卫星进行了维护
but these are primarily there to provide attitude control and propulsion.
但这些任务主要是提供姿态控制和推进的
They basically fly up behind it and attached to the satellite through one of the thrusters.
基本上是飞到卫星后面 通过(目标卫星的其中一个)推进器连接上去
And then there the mission is able to continue.
然后让任务得以继续进行
But in this case the computer that's failing is something that manages all the payloads.
但在这种情况下 发生故障的计算机是管理所有有效载荷的东西
It's not just a case of providing attitude control.
这不仅仅是一个提供姿态控制的情况
So it's not clear that an autonomous spacecraft could actually repair the Hubble Space Telescope right now.
因此 现在还不清楚一个无人航天器是否能真正修复哈勃太空望远镜
www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2021/operations-underway-to-restore-payload-computer-on-nasas-hubble-space-telescope，
2021年7月17日，在切换到了备份的电源控制单元(Power Control Unit，PCU)和
指令单元/科学数据格式化单元(Command Unit/Science Data Formatter，CU/SDF)后恢复运行
I'm pretty confident that they will recover some operations of Hubble.
我很有信心 NASA会恢复哈勃的一些操作
They may not recover 100% right now.
他们现在可能不会100%恢复
But I'm hoping that we get more life from this fantastic instrument
但我希望能延续这个美妙仪器的寿命
and because it deserves to fly for many years more.
因为它值得再飞很多年
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]